<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ansvvere made by the kynges hyghnes to the petitions of the rebelles in Yorkeshire</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1536</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13077</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109524</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845171</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845171</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10057</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02937)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10057)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 49:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ansvvere made by the kynges hyghnes to the petitions of the rebelles in Yorkeshire</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In aedibus Thomae Bertheleti regii impressoris],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. M.D.XXXVI. 1536.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶.</note>
                  <note>Bound with STC 13077.5 (formerly STC 15650): Answere to the petitions of the traytours and rebelles in Lyncolneshyre.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Yorkshire (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10057:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 127 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10057:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 127 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>ANSVVERE MADE BY THE KYNGES HYGHNES TO <hi>the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the rebelles in Yorkeſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>ANNO. M.D.XXXVI.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10057:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 128 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10057:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 128 -->
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>YRSTE AS TOVCHYNGE</hi> the mayntenance of the faythe, the termes be ſo generall, that it wolde be very harde to make certaine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the ſame, but if they mean the faithe of Chriſte, to the whiche all chriſten menne be only bounde, We declare and proteſte our ſelfe to be that prince, that dothe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende and hath always mynded to lyue and dye in the mayntenaunce defence and obſeruation of the puritie of the ſame, And that no man can or dare ſet his fote by vs in prouynge of the contrary. We meruayle therfore moche, that ignoraunt people woll go about to take vpon them, to inſtructe and teche vs, which haue ben noted ſomthynge lerned, What the feyth ſhuld be, and alſo that they being ignorant people, be ſo preſumptuous (ſeinge that we and our hole clergy in conuocation haue in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles declared it) to take vpon them to correcte vs all therin: or that they wold be ſo ingrate and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall towardes vs, theyr moſte rightfull kyng and ſoueraigne lorde, without any our deſerte, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon fals reportes or ſurmyſes, to ſuſpect vs of the ſame, and gyue rather credence to forged lyght ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, than to the very trouthe by vs theſe .xxviii. ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res vſed, and by our dedes approued.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>TO THE</hi> ſecond, which towcheth the mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the church &amp; the lyberties of the ſame, we ſaye, It is ſo generall a propoſicion, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtinctions no man can well aunſwere it. For
<pb facs="tcp:10057:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 129 -->fyrſte the churche, which they meane, muſt be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen. Seconde whyther thoſe thinges, whych they calle lyberties, and ſaye they wolde maynteyne, be thinges lawfull and beneficiall to the prynce and common welthe, or otherwyſe. And theſe knowen, we doubt not, but they ſhal be anſwered according to goddis lawes equitie and Iuſtyce. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les for al their generalite this we dare affirme, that meanynge what churche they lyſt, we haue doone nothynge, that maye not be abyden by, bothe by goddis lawes and mans lawes: or that is preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall to the common welthe, if our procedynges may be indifferently wayed and conſydered. And in our owne churche of Englande, whereof we be the ſupreme heed in erthe, we haue done nothynge ſo onerous and chargeable to theym, as many of our predeceſſours haue doone vppon moche leſſe grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. For dyd not kynge Edwarde the thyrde, of moſt noble memory our progenitour, ſuppreſſe all the monaſteries of one hole religion, that were within this realme, and conuerted theym holly to his owne vſe, ſauynge a certayne of the ſame, that he gaue to his noble men and gentyll men, as we haue at this tyme lyke wyſe done? Dyd not kyng Henry the .v. ſuppreſſe aboue one hundreth mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteryes, takynge the greate benefite of the ſame to his owne propre vſe and behoufe? And what acte dyd he agayne within this realme, that coulde be noted to the prouffite of the common weale of the ſame, onles it were the erection of Syon, and the houſe of the Charterhouſe at Shene? Dydde not
<pb facs="tcp:10057:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 129 -->kynge Henry the .vi. ſemblably ſuppreſſe a good nombre of monaſteries for the makynge of a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege in Cambridge, and yet neuertheles but a very fewe of them were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted to the vſe therof? Dyd not our Grandame in lyke maner, for the edifieng of two colleges in our vniuerſitie of Cambridge, procure the ſuppreſſion of a great many houſes of religion? Dyd not byſhop Alcock, beinge noted a good man, procure the ſuppreſſion of certayn mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries for the building of an other college with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſame vninerſitie? Dyd not the cardinall of yorke lately for the erectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a college in Oxforde, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe the ſup<g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſſion of thirty monaſteries? Howe many byſhops beſydes, as of Canturbury, Wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter, Rocheſter, Lyncolne, &amp; others, haue procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the putting downe of abbeys, for the buylding and endowementes of dyuers Colleges, whiche ſundry of them haue made within dyuers vnyuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, and alſo for ſundrie other purpoſes and fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations? Wherfore ſythens this article perteynith nothyng to any of our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons, nor that they beare any thynge therin, we can not but recken a greate vnkyndenes and vnnaturalnes in theym, whiche had leauer a chorle or twayne ſhulde enioye thoſe profites of their monaſteryes, for the ſupportation and mayntenaunce of abhomynable lyfe, thanne that we their prince ſhuld receyue the ſame, to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des our extreme charges done and daily ſuſteyned for their defence agaynſt forayn ennemies.</p>
            <p>¶ The thirde article toucheth thre thynges. The fyrſt is the lawes: The ſecond is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth:
<pb facs="tcp:10057:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 130 -->The thirde the directours of the lawes vnder vs. Touchynge the lawes, as it becometh not blynde men to iudge any colours, ne to take vpon theym to be iudges in the ſame, ſo we dare expreſſely and boldly affirme, as a thynge that may be eaſily and duely proued, that there was neuer in any one of our predeceſſours dayes, ſo many holſom commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and beneficiall actes made for the common welth, as haue ben made in our tyme, and ſythens ſome of them hadde credite and doynge in our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres, that wolde nowe perchaunce fayne pycke them thanke without deſerte: for our lord forbede, that bothe we and our counſayle ſhulde haue loſte ſo moche tyme, as not to knowe better nowe, than we dyd in the begynnyng of our reigne, what were a common welth, and what were againſt the good and commoditie of the ſame, ſeinge we haue ben a kynge theſe .xxviii. yeres, and by experience lerned the perfytenes therof. and all thoughe the folye and vnkyndnes of ſome wol not percaſe ſo know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege it: yet we truſte and doubte not, but the moſt parte of our louyng ſubiectes, ſpecially thoſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be not ſeduced by fals reportes, do both thinke it, accepte it, and fynde it ſoo.</p>
            <p>¶ Nowe touchyng the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welthe, what kyng hath kepte his ſubiectis ſo longe in welth &amp; peace, ſo longe without takynge or doing wronge one to an other, ſo indyfferently minyſtred Iuſtice to all eſtates bothe hygh and lowe, ſo defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded them from al outwarde ennemies, ſo fortified the fronters of his realme, to his no lytell and in maner ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:10057:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 130 -->charges, and all for their welthes and ſureties? What kynge hathe gyuen amonge his ſubiectes mo generall or free pardons? What kynge hath ben lother to punyſh his ſubiectis, or ſhewed more mercy amonges them? Theſe thynges beinge ſoo true, as no true man can denye them, It is an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall &amp; an vnkynd demeanour of you our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectis, to beleue or deny the contrary of it, by whoſe reporte ſo euer it ſhuld be ſet forth ageynſt vs.</p>
            <p>¶ And touchynge the begynnyng of our reygne, where it is ſayde, that ſo many noble menne were counſaylours, we do not forget, who were thenne of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayle. For of the temporaltie, there were but two worthy to be called noble, the one the trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſorer of Englande, the other the hyghe Steward of our houſholde, others, as the lord Marney and Darcy, but meane borne gentylmen, ne yet of any great landes, tyl they were promoted by the kinge our father of moſt noble memorie, &amp; by vs, and ſo made knyghtes &amp; lordes. The reſt were lawiers &amp; preſtes, ſauyng the two byſhoppes of Canturbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Wyncheſire. If theſe then be the great no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of noble men, that is ſpoken of, &amp; that our ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes ſemed at that tyme to be contented withall, why then be they not nowe moche better conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with vs, whiche haue ſo many nobles in dede, bothe of byrthe and condition, of our counſayle. For fyrſte of the temporaltie, in our priuye coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, we haue the Duke of Norfolke, the Duke of Suffolke, the Marques of Exceſter, the lorde Stewarde, whenne he is preſente, the Erle of
<pb facs="tcp:10057:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 131 -->Oxforde, The Erle of Suſſex, the lorde Sandes, our Chamberlayne, the lorde Admyral, treaſorer of our houſe, ſyr wyllyam Poulet Comptroller of our houſe, ſyr Wyllyam Kyngſton our vicecham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlayne, And of the ſpiritualtie, the byſhoppes of Canturbury, Wyncheſter, Hereford, and Chiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. And for bycauſe it is more then neceſſary, to haue ſome of our pryuy counſaylle lerned in our lawes, and acqueynted with the polycies &amp; prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes of the worlde, we, by thaduiſe of our hole cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle before named, did electe and choſe into our priuye counſayle, and alſo into theyr roumes, ſire Thomas Audeley knyght, our Chancellour, and the lorde Crumwel, keper of our priuy ſeale, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge them men in all our opinions mooſte mete for the ſame roumes. And we with our hole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle thynke it ryghte ſtraunge, that you, whiche be but ignorant and vnexpert folkes, ſhulde take vppon you to appoynte and limitte to vs, who be mete to be of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl, and who be not. Marke therfore nowe, howe theſe ſedicious perſons, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſo wrongfully haue borne you thus in hande, haue falſely abuſed you, that reaken, there were then moo noble men of our priuie counſaile, then be nowe. But yet thoughe of our great clemency &amp; princely goodnes, we declare now the truthe, to pul you our ſubiectes from that errour and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes you be trayned and brought into, by falſe and vntrue ſurmyſes, and reportes: we wold agayne, that euery of you knowe, that it apperteyneth not to any ſubiecte, to preſume to take vppon hym, to
<pb facs="tcp:10057:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 131 -->appoynte his kynge and ſoueraigne lordis coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, ne for our part we wol take any ſuch thing at any of our ſubiectes handes. Wherfore we wolde, that from hensforth, they ſhulde better remembre the duities of good ſubiectis towardes their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral liege lorde, and medel not with theſe and ſuche lyke thynges, as they haue nothinge to do withal.</p>
            <p>¶ To the .iiii. article, where the comons do name certayne of our counſaile to be ſubuerters both of goddis lawe and the lawes of the realme, we doo take and repute them, as iuſt and true executours bothe of goddis lawes and of ours, as farre as theyr commiſſions vnder vs do extende. And if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our ſubiectes can duely proue the contrary, we ſhall procede ageynſt them, and all other offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours therin, accordynge to Iuſtice, as to our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and dignitie royall doth apperteyne. And in caſe it be but a falſe and an vntrue reporte, as we veryly thynk it is, then it were as mete, and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth as wel with iuſtice, that they ſhulde haue the ſelfe ſame punyſhement, whiche wrongfully haue obiected this to them, that they ſhuld haue had, if they hadde deſerued it. And one thyng amonges others cauſeth vs to thynke, that this ſklaunder ſhulde be vntrue, bycauſe it procedeth from that place, whiche is bothe farre diſtante from that, where they inhabyte, and alſo from thoſe people, which neuer harde them preache, nor yet knoweth any parte of theyr conuerſation. Wherfore we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte you al our comons of thoſe parties, to be no more ſo light of credyte in the beleuynge of euyll
<pb facs="tcp:10057:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 132 -->thynges, ſpoken of vs your naturall prynce and ſoueraigne lorde, nor of any of our counſailours or prelates, but to thynke, that your kynge, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge ſoo longe reigned ouer you, hath as good diſcretion, to elect and choſe his counſaylours, by thaduyſe of his counſayle before named, as thoſe what ſoeuer they be, that haue put this into your heades, and moche better thenne you, being but ignorant people, and out of al experience of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis affayres, can haue. And as vnto the laſt arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and alſo vnto the mater of the hole dyſcours of your peticions, we veryly thynke, that the reſt of all our hole commons, of many countreys, to whom you be in maner but an handful, wyl gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſdayne, and not beare it, that you take vpon you, to ſet order to vs and them, and ſpecially to vs beinge ſoueraygne lord to you bothe: and that you beinge rebelles, wold make them as bearers and parttakers of your miſchiefe, wyllynge them to take pardon for inſurrections, whyche veryly we thynke and doubt not, they neuer mynded, but lyke true ſubiectes, to the contrary haue both with harte and dede bene redy at our calle, to defende bothe vs and them ſelfes.</p>
            <p>¶ And nowe for our parte, as to your demandes, we late you wyte, that pardon of ſuche thynges, as you demaunde, lyethe onely in the wylle and pleaſure of vs your ſoueraygne lorde and prince: But it ſemeth by your lewde proclamations and ſaufe conductis, that there be amonges you, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che take vppon them bothe the partes of kynges
<pb facs="tcp:10057:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 132 -->and of counſaylours, whiche neither by vs nor by the generall conſent of our realme, haue ben ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to any ſuch rome. What arrogancy is then in thoſe wretches, being alſo of none experience, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wol preſume to reiſe you our ſubiectis without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion or auctoritie, ye &amp; agaynſt vs, vnder a clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked color of your welth, and in our name, &amp; as the ſucceſſion and ende wol declare, if we ſhuld not be more mercyful vnto you, than you haue deſerued, to your owne vtter confuſions? Wherfore we late all you our ſayde ſubiectes again witte, that were it not, that our pryncely harte can not reken this your ſhameful inſurrection, and moſt ingrate and vnnaturall rebellion, to haue ben done of malyce or rancour, but rather by a lightnes of credite gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in maner by a naughty nature to a comminal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and a wonderous ſodayn ſurrection of gentyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, we muſt nedes haue executed an other maner of punyſhement, than if you wyll humbly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge your fawte, and ſubmytte your ſelfes to our mercy, we entende to do, as by our proclamations, we doubt not but you be informed. And now ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore note our benignitie, nowe conſidre howe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we deſire the preſeruation of you our ſubiectis, and thaduoydynge of theffuſion of chriſten blode, and nowe conſider, what hurte you haue in this lyttell tyme done vnto your ſelfes, and lerne by this gentyl refourmation, to auoyde a greatter y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, to loue honour and dreade your prynce and ſoueraine lorde, that thus tendreth you, and from hensforthe to lyue lyke true ſubiectes to vs, and to beleue no moo ſuche fals and lyght tales.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:10057:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 133 -->
            <p>LONDINI IN AEDIBVS THOMAE BER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THELETI RECII IMPRES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SORIS.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>CVM PRIVILEGIO.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10057:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 133 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
